<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux | SysAdmin's Journey]]></title>
  <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-12T16:34:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Ellison]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lead SysAdmin position available]]></title>
    <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2011/04/06/lead-sysadmin-position-available"/>
    <updated>2011-04-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2011/04/06/lead-sysadmin-position-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There's a blog post to follow with when/why, etc., but without
further ado: I'm moving to a new position at Buckle, and that means
we need a new Lead SysAdmin.  It's a great job at a great company,
in a great place to raise a family (Kearney, NE).  You get paid
well, get a good yearly budget for new toys, and equipment, and
it's overall a very fun position. If interested, <a href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/contact">drop me a
line</a>, and I'll make sure your
resume gets the proper attention.  To apply online, <a href="https://storefront.kenexa.com/buckle/cc/CCJobSearchAction.ss?command=CCSearchPage">click
here</a>,
and search for jobs within 5 miles of zip code 68845.  The job
title is "Web Development - Lead Systems Administrator". Here's the
job posting: JOB DETAIL Job Title:  ** Web Development - Lead
Systems Administrator**
<img src="https://storefront.kenexa.com/buckle/cc/images/orange_line.gif" alt="image" />
Location:  Buckle Corporate Office &amp; Distribution Center  2407 W
24th Street  KEARNEY, Nebraska 68845-0000
<img src="https://storefront.kenexa.com/buckle/cc/images/orange_line.gif" alt="image" />
Job Description:  ### Lead Systems Administrator **Position
Summary:** The Lead Systems Administrator will be responsible for
the deployment and maintenance of Unix/Linux systems and
application software in multiple environments. The ideal candidate
will possess a deep understanding of large scale Unix deployments
and will lead the team responsible for the infrastructure serving
all e-commerce and intranet applications. Additionally, this person
must be able to function effectively in a fast-paced environment
where projects range from maintenance to upgrades to new
deployments and technologies. Our Systems Administrators also serve
as Network Administrators for the smaller networks their systems
reside in, so strong knowledge of ethernet, TCP/IP, and network
security is required. **Responsibilities:** • Maintain all
servers and workstations on WSD team, including production,
development, and staging of servers for the e-commerce platform and
company intranet • Setup, maintain, and manage an enterprise-class
backup strategy for WSD team servers and workstations • Automate
tasks via custom scripting • Assist in architecting and designing
solid server solutions **Requirements:** • Expertise in setting
up robust and reliable server architectures. Additionally, a large
appetite for automating the mundane is preferred and will be
encouraged. ● In-depth knowledge of technologies that include but
are not limited to: Linux systems administration, Java VM tuning,
Weblogic Administration, Apache HTTPD/NGINX Administration, All
layers of TCP/IP, subnetting, etc., IPSEC VPN’s, ISC BIND, Load
balancing and clustering technologies, Shell scripting, Nagios
monitoring and RRD administration, RPM packaging format and
patching best practices • A bachelor’s degree in Computer Science
or other discipline • Minimum 4-5 years of previous
system-administration experience in a professional environment
**Compensation:** Market/negotiable, relocation assistance is a
possibility for the right candidate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apache mod_proxy '[error] (13)Permission denied' error on RHEL]]></title>
    <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2010/02/01/apache-modproxy-error-13permission-denied-error-rhel"/>
    <updated>2010-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2010/02/01/apache-mod_proxy-error-13permission-denied-error-on-rhel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Had an interesting issue today working on a mod_proxy setup of Apache
forwarding requests in a reverse proxy setup to a backend Tomcat server. No
matter what I did, I kept getting this in Apache's error log:</p>

<pre><code>[error] (13)Permission denied: proxy: AJP: attempt to connect to 10.x.x.x:7009 (virtualhost.virtualdomain.com) failed
</code></pre>

<p>I thought for sure it was proxy permissions, but nothing I did fixed the
issue. Then it hit me: SELinux! Why I always think of SELinux last when it's
responsible for 90% of my problems, I'll never know. SELinux on RHEL/CentOS by
default ships so that httpd processes cannot initiate outbound connections,
which is just what mod_proxy attempts to do. If this is your problem, you'll
see something like this in /var/log/audit/audit.log:</p>

<pre><code>type=AVC msg=audit(1265039669.305:14): avc:  denied  { name_connect } for  pid=4343 comm="httpd" dest=7009 
scontext=system_u:system_r:httpd_t:s0 tcontext=system_u:object_r:port_t:s0 tclass=tcp_socket
</code></pre>

<p>To fix this, first test by setting the boolean dynamically (not permanent
yet):</p>

<pre><code> /usr/sbin/setsebool httpd_can_network_connect 1
</code></pre>

<p>If that works, you can set it so that the default policy is changed and this
setting will persist across reboots:</p>

<pre><code> /usr/sbin/setsebool -P httpd_can_network_connect 1
</code></pre>

<p>Hope this saves others some time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[QuickTip: Make life easier with ssh-copy-id]]></title>
    <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/11/12/quicktip-make-life-easier-ssh-copy-id"/>
    <updated>2009-11-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/11/12/quicktip-make-life-easier-with-ssh-copy-id</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How many times have you ran through this series of events?
<div>
  <pre><code class='console'>$ cat ~/.ssh/id_dsa.pub
...copy output to clipboard...
$ ssh myhost
...enter password...
myhost$ vi ~./ssh/authorized_keys
...paste public key and save...
myhost$ exit</code></pre>
</div>

Thanks to bash's tab completion, I
happened upon <strong>ssh-copy-id</strong>. Instead of all that above, just do this:
<div>
  <pre><code class='console'>$ ssh-copy-id myhost
...enter password...</code></pre>
</div>

You're done!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Reboot After Adding Partitions - partprobe!]]></title>
    <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/08/20/dont-reboot-after-adding-partitions-partprobe"/>
    <updated>2009-08-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/08/20/dont-reboot-after-adding-partitions-partprobe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/gnu-head.png" alt="" />Another one of those topics where about 50% of
the class bustled in excitement over learning something new and simple came up
today. After running fdisk, you will almost always get an error about the
kernel not using the new partition table you just modified. Before GNU
released parted, you had to reboot in order for the kernel to purge it's cache
and reload the partition table, but now, all you need to do is run
<strong>partprobe</strong> after exiting fdisk. AFAIK, partprobe is included in most all
distros.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RedHat 6 Tidbits]]></title>
    <link href="http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/08/18/redhat-6-tidbits"/>
    <updated>2009-08-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sysadminsjourney.com/content/2009/08/18/redhat-6-tidbits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/logo_rh_home.png" alt="RedHat" />During my <a href="https://www.redhat%0A.com/courses/rh300_rhce_rapid_track_course_and_rhce_exam/">RH300</a> course, my
instructor mentioned that RHEL 6 is likely to come out sometime Q1 2010. I
wanted to know more about it, so I hit Google, and came up with some
interesting results.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions%0A/red-hat-31/when-we-shall-expect-rhel-6-711537/">This post over at linuxquestions.org</a> starts out innocently enough
-- someone asks for an expected release data on RHEL 6. A poster named
<strong>lazlow</strong> who appears to be a RH or Fedora dev gives a few interesting
tidbits:</p>

<ul>
<li>RHEL 5 is based on Fedora Core 6. No wonder it feels a little long in the tooth!</li>
<li>RHEL 6 was intended to be based upon Fedora 9, but it had too many bugs to even be considered.</li>
<li><strong>Since the Fedora development has been driven by the community, the focus has shifted towards new features</strong>. I've seen this before in community driven projects. Unless devs are motivated either via cash or fixing the bug helps their situation, no one wants to fix bugs. New features are more fun to work on.</li>
<li>To solve the problem, <strong>RedHat didn't take the project out of the community's hands, they paid their own devs to fix Fedora bugs</strong>. This is very commendable behavior for a big corporation, and I feel it's a win/win for RedHat and the community.</li>
<li>It looks like RHEL6 will be based upon Fedora 11.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, this could all be someone spouting off about things they don't know
anything about, but it looks like it checks out to me. Some pretty interesting
tidbits, and (if true) an example of a corporation contributing to OSS and
making money off of it. If anyone can confirm or deny this information, please
do so!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
